<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Borel-fixed ideal on Roberta&#39;s Personal Web Page</title>
    <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/tags/borel-fixed-ideal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Borel-fixed ideal on Roberta&#39;s Personal Web Page</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.robertasirovich.it/tags/borel-fixed-ideal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Rational components of Hilbert schemes</title>
      <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/lr/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/lr/</guid>
      <description>Abstract. The Gröbner stratum of a monomial ideal $J$ is an affine variety that parametrizes the family of all ideals having $J$ as initial ideal (with respect to a fixed term ordering). The Gröbner strata can be equipped in a natural way of a structure of homogeneous variety and are in a close connection with Hilbert schemes of subvarieties in the projective space $\mathbb{P}^n$. Using properties of the Gröbner strata we prove some sufficient conditions for the rationality of components of $\mathbf{Hilb}_{p(z)}(\mathbb{P}^n)$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Segments and Hilbert schemes of points</title>
      <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/clmr/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/clmr/</guid>
      <description>Abstract. Using results obtained from the study of homogeneous ideals sharing the same initial ideal with respect to some term order, we prove the singularity of the point corresponding to a segment ideal with respect to the revlex term order in the Hilbert scheme of points in $\mathbb{P}^n$. In this context, we look inside properties of several types of &amp;ldquo;segment&amp;rdquo; ideals that we define and compare. This study led us to focus our attention also to connections between the shape of generators of Borel ideals and the related Hilbert polynomial, providing an algorithm for computing all saturated Borel ideals with the given Hilbert polynomial.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An efficient implementation of the algorithm computing the Borel-fixed points of a Hilbert scheme</title>
      <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/issac/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/issac/</guid>
      <description>Abstract. Borel-fixed ideals play a key role in the study of Hilbert schemes. Indeed each component and each intersection of components of a Hilbert scheme contains at least one Borel-fixed point, i.e. a point corresponding to a subscheme defined by a Borel-fixed ideal. Moreover Borel-fixed ideals have good combinatorial properties, which make them very interesting in an algorithmic perspective. In this paper, we propose an implementation of the algorithm computing all the saturated Borel-fixed ideals with number of variables and Hilbert polynomial assigned, introduced from a theoretical point of view in the paper Cioffi-Lella-Marinari-Roggero, Segment ideals and Hilbert schemes of points, Discrete Mathematics 311(20), 2011.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upgraded methods for the effective computation of marked schemes on a strongly stable ideal</title>
      <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/bclr/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/bclr/</guid>
      <description>Abstract. Let $J \subset S=K[x_0,\ldots,x_n]$ be a monomial strongly stable ideal. The collection $\mathbf{Mf}(J)$ of the homogeneous polynomial ideals $I$, such that the monomials outside $J$ form a $K$-vector basis of $S/I$, is called a $J$-marked family. It can be endowed with a structure of affine scheme, called a $J$-marked scheme. For special ideals $J$, $J$-marked schemes provide an open cover of the Hilbert scheme $\mathbf{Hilb}_{p(t)}(\mathbb{P}^n)$, where $p(t)$ is the Hilbert polynomial of $S/J$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Borel open cover of the Hilbert scheme</title>
      <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/blr/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/blr/</guid>
      <description>Abstract. Let $p(t)$ be an admissible Hilbert polynomial in $\mathbb{P}^n$ of degree $d$. The Hilbert scheme $\mathbf{Hilb}_{p(t)}(\mathbb{P}^n)$ can be realized as a closed subscheme of a suitable Grassmannian $\mathbf{Gr}$, hence it could be globally defined by homogeneous equations in the Plücker coordinates of $\mathbf{Gr}$ and covered by open subsets given by the non-vanishing of a Plücker coordinate, each embedded as a closed subscheme of the affine space $\mathbb{A}^D$, $D=\dim(\mathbf{Gr})$. However, the number $E$ of Plücker coordinates is so large that effective computations in this setting are practically impossible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Minimal Castelnuovo-Mumford regularity for a given Hilbert polynomial</title>
      <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/clmr2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/clmr2/</guid>
      <description>Abstract. Let $K$ be an algebraically closed field of null characteristic and $p(z)$ a Hilbert polynomial. We look for the minimal Castelnuovo-Mumford regularity $m_{p(z)}$ of closed subschemes of projective spaces over $K$ with Hilbert polynomial $p(z)$. Experimental evidences led us to consider the idea that $m_{p(z)}$ could be achieved by schemes having a suitable minimal Hilbert function. We give a constructive proof of this fact. Moreover, we are able to compute the minimal Castelnuovo-Mumford regularity $m_{p(z)}^{\varrho}$ of schemes with Hilbert polynomial $p(z)$ and given regularity $\varrho$ of the Hilbert function, and also the minimal Castelnuovo-Mumford regularity $m_u$ of schemes with Hilbert function $u$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extensors and the Hilbert scheme</title>
      <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/blmr/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/blmr/</guid>
      <description>Abstract. The Hilbert scheme $\mathbf{Hilb}_{p(t)}(\mathbb{P}^n)$ parametrizes closed subschemes and families of closed subschemes in the projective space $\mathbb{P}^n$ with a fixed Hilbert polynomial $p(t)$. It can be realized as a closed subscheme of a Grassmannian or a product of Grassmannians. In this paper we consider schemes over a field $k$ of characteristic zero and we present a new proof of the existence of the Hilbert scheme as a subscheme of the Grassmannian $\mathbf{Gr}_{p(r)}^{N(r)}$, where $N(r)=h^0\big(\mathcal{O}_{\mathbb{P}^n}(r)\big)$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the functoriality of marked families</title>
      <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/lr2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/lr2/</guid>
      <description>Abstract. The application of methods of computational algebra has recently introduced new tools for the study of Hilbert schemes. The key idea is to define flat families of ideals endowed with a scheme structure whose defining equations can be determined by algorithmic procedures. For this reason, several authors developed new methods, based on the combinatorial properties of Borel-fixed ideals, that allow to associate to each ideal $J$ of this type a scheme $\mathbf{Mf}(J)$, called $J$-marked scheme.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strongly stable ideals and Hilbert polynomials</title>
      <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/al/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/al/</guid>
      <description>Abstract. The StronglyStableIdeals.m2 package for Macaulay2 provides a method to compute all saturated strongly stable ideals in a given polynomial ring with a fixed Hilbert polynomial. A description of the main method and auxiliary tools is given.
 Ancillary Material  Macaulay2 package StronglyStableIdeals.m2.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computing marked families via sygyzy forecasting</title>
      <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/bcl/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/bcl/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the tangent space to the Hilbert scheme</title>
      <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/ltangent/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/ltangent/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MarkedSchemes.m2 - A M2 package for marked schemes and Groebner strata</title>
      <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/lm2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/lm2/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
