<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>vector bundle on Roberta&#39;s Personal Web Page</title>
    <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/tags/vector-bundle/</link>
    <description>Recent content in vector bundle on Roberta&#39;s Personal Web Page</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.robertasirovich.it/tags/vector-bundle/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Truncated modules and linear presentations of vector bundles</title>
      <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/bfl/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/bfl/</guid>
      <description>Abstract. We give a new method to construct linear spaces of matrices of constant rank, based on truncated graded cohomology modules of certain vector bundles as well as on the existence of graded Artinian modules with pure resolutions. Our method allows one to produce several new examples, and provides an alternative point of view on the existing ones.
 Ancillary Material  Macaulay2 package ConstantRankMatrices.m2 for computing matrices of constant rank.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A construction of equivariant bundles on the space of symmetric forms</title>
      <link>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/bfl2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertasirovich.it/publications/bfl2/</guid>
      <description>Abstract. We construct stable vector bundles on the space of symmetric forms of degree $d$ in $n+1$ variables which are equivariant for the action of $\text{SL}_{n+1}(\mathbb{C})$, and admit an equivariant free resolution of length 2. For $n=1$, we obtain new examples of stable vector bundles of rank $d-1$ on $\mathbb{P}^d$, which are moreover equivariant for $\text{SL}_2(\mathbb{C})$. The presentation matrix of these bundles attains Westwick&amp;rsquo;s upper bound for the dimension of vector spaces of matrices of constant rank and fixed size.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
